Guide to the American Dance Festival Records, circa 1924-1985, bulk 1934-1977 ADF.015
American Dance Festival Archives
- Special Projects, 1947-1985 (Box 23)
  - Music and Dance (MAD), 1974-1977, 5 folders (Box 26)
    In 1974, Project: Music and Dance (MAD), also known as the Composers-Choreographers Workshop, paired experienced choreographers with composers to create new works. The works created through the collaborations were Bella Lewitzky's Fire, music by Max Lifchitz, Jennifer Muller's Winter Pieces, music by Charles O. B. Curtis-Smith, Manuel Alum's Yemaya, music by Ira Taxin, and Nancy Meehan's Yellow Paint, music by Rocco di Pietra. The music was performed by the St. Paul Chamber Orchestra under the direction of Dennis Russel Davies. In 1975, MAD teamed Kathryn Posin and composer Laurie Spiegel and Pilobolus and composer Robert Dennis. 1976 included Murray Louis's Glances to music by Dave Brubeck.
  - Other Projects, 1947-1977, 9 folders (Box 26)
    Contains programs, administrative materials, diagrams, newspaper clippings, artwork, correspondence, schedules, form letters, contracts, and a NEA grant application referring to a variety of projects with some association with the American Dance Festival, Dance Symposiums held by the Connecticut College Dance Group featuring classes and critiques by Louis Horst, Walter Terry, Hazel Johnson, June Dunbar, Ella Lukk, Pauline Koner, and David Wood (1954 and 1958), children's programs by the Merry-Go-Rounders and the Merrymobile (1959), international projects (1959 and 1961), a documentary on the American Dance Festival (1972), and the Total Theatre Project film Taylor's Follies (1975-1977).
- Press and Publicity Materials, 1934-1977 (Box 26)
  - Press Coverage, 1934-1977, 2.25 Linear Feet (Box 26)
    Contains press clippings referring to the American Dance Festival and its performers and participants.
    Individual files devoted to Martha Graham, Hanya Holm, and Louis Horst, are followed by files arranged chronologically.
    - 1934-1968 (Box 26)
    - 1969-1977 (Box 27)
    - Press Book, 1974 (Box OS1)
  - Press Kits, 1974-1975, 4 folders (Box 28)
    Contains press kits made and distributed by ADF containing press releases describing the various activities at the school and festival including schedules of events, companies performing at the festival, festival programs, projects offered by the Community Outreach Program, and workshops and mini-conferences including the Critics Conference and the Dance Educators' Workshop. Also includes individual companies' publicity materials that were distributed as part of the general press kits.
  - Press Releases, 1936, 1948-1977, 0.58 Linear Feet (Box 28)
    Contains press releases, schedules, correspondence, and lists of students organized according to home state for publicity purposes. Releases include information on faculty members, classes, artists, programs to be held, and descriptions of programs after the performances. Also includes correspondence regarding press releases, ticket order forms, and administrative materials.
- School, 1934-1988 and undated (Box 28)
  - School Administration, 1947-1977 (Box 28)
    - Academic Credit, 1948-1977 and undated, 31 folders (Box 28)
      Contains letters of interest, correspondence, notes, student lists, credit explanations, form letters, and administrative materials that address ADF's policies and practices toward academic credit in relation to ADF courses. Records address Connecticut College students receiving academic credit for ADF courses, inquiries from other academic institutions about ADF's course work, and inquiries from students regarding academic credit. Also includes correspondence initiated by ADF with similar summer dance schools and programs regarding academic credit.
    - Administration, 1947-1977, 2.75 Linear Feet (Box 28)
      Contains ADF School administrative materials such as information about school policies, procedures, programs, and student application and registration, forms and form letters, letters of interest from prospective students and faculty, correspondence with faculty and students unable to attend, information about mass mailings, schedules for classes (working copies), master calendars, weekly status reports about school applicants, correspondence, and notes. Subseries is organized chronologically with categories within each year. Items of interest include correspondence with faculty unable to attend, such as Mary Wigman (1951), Anna Halprin (1958), Merce Cunningham (1962), Norman and Ruth Lloyd (1962), Eleo Pomare (1965), and Martha Graham (1968).
      - 1947-1959 (Box 28)
      - 1960-1970 (Box 29)
      - 1971-1977 and undated (Box 30)
    - Advisory Board, 1956-1973, 12 folders (Box 31)
      Contains correspondence, agenda, meeting minutes, and notes pertaining to the planning of the ADF School and the upcoming season. The Advisory Board, in conjunction with the Festival Committee, was the decision-making body for nearly all activities of the School of Dance and the Festival season including faculty, accompanists, workshops, scholarships and scholarship winners, the dates of the school, and special projects. The Board also made decisions about funding and administrative personnel.
    - Dance Costumes, 1948-1969, 14 folders (Box 31)
      Contains correspondence between the ADF School and Wright and Ditson, a dance clothing supply house, discussing the styles and colors of the regulation costume, consisting of a choice of leotard and tights, required by the ADF School. Also includes Wright and Ditson order forms and notices to students about their dance attire.
    - Dance Medicine and Infirmary, 1948-1977, 15 folders (Box 31)
      Contains statistical reports of ailments and injuries treated by the Connecticut College infirmary, correspondence between ADF and Connecticut College regarding usage of the infirmary during the summer, and general information about the infirmary hours and emergency contacts for students.
    - Housing, Meals, and Car Registration, 1948-1977 and undated, 1.0 Linear Feet (Box 31)
      Contains housing and dining room lists, dormitory floor plans, correspondence, forms, housing meeting minutes, meal tickets, notes regarding housing preferences and decisions, and car registration forms. Also includes completed questionnaires or information from local residents who rented their homes to members of the ADF community.
    - Recruitment, 1961-1974 and undated, 4 folders (Box 31)
      Contains materials, such as mailing lists of college dance departments and forms for a traveling ADF School photo exhibit, concerning the recruitment of students for the school.
  - Curriculum, 1934-1977 (Box 32)
    - Bulletins and Catalogs, 1934-1977, 33 folders (Box 32)
      Contains school catalogs or bulletins listing faculty, classes, and other school information. Drafts of the catalogs and bulletins, proof copies, or administrative materials concerning the creation or printing of catalogs and bulletins are filed in Administration under the Publications Office series.
    - Children's Classes, 1950-1969, 17 folders (Box 32)
      Contains correspondence, forms and form letters, class lists, applications, and course materials relating to classes for children (under 12) at Connecticut College for young non-residential students. Children's classes were distinct from the ADF's community classes offered by the Community Outreach Program and the program was known alternately as the Young Dancers Workshop and the Childrens Dance Workshop. Teachers included Ruth Ferguson, Harriet Berg, Bonnie Bird, and Virginia Tanner.
    - Class Auditions, 1967-1976, 10 folders (Box 32)
      Contains audition lists and audition schedules relating to required group auditions held for technique class placement at the beginning of the summer term. Also includes correspondence, notes, schedules, and procedure lists for arranging and holding auditions.
    - Class Schedules, 1938-1977, 0.25 Linear Feet (Box 32)
      Contains tentative and final printed schedules of classes offered during the summer session.
    - Courses, 1948-1977 and undated, 1.0 Linear Feet (Box 32)
      Contains information about various courses and special workshops, including course descriptions, teachers' and students' notes, syllabi, blank exams, handouts, and handbooks.
      Arranged chronologically and arranged alphabetically within each year by course title.
      - 1948-1970 (Box 32)
      - 1971-1977 and undated (Box 33)
    - Development, 1949-1977, 17 folders (Box 33)
      Contains memoranda, correspondence, minutes, and notes recording discussions, meetings, and suggestions about the development of the school as a whole and its curricula, faculty, and quality of applicants. Also included are correspondence and curriculum proposals by Bessie Schonberg. Of interest are the 1967-1968 proposals of a Master of Arts in Dance with a teaching emphasis or a Master of Arts in Fine Arts through the ADF School. Also of interest are the notes on the development of the Theater Component (1976) and Weekend Workshops (1977).
    - Informal Showings, 1948-1975, 27 folders (Box 33)
      Contains programs, program materials, memoranda, correspondence, and sign-up sheets regarding informal performances of student choreography, improvisation, and movement studies. Class Showings were informal programs of specific classes, performed by students and reflecting their "in progress" work developed during their daily classes. Student Workshops were informal weekly performances, and approximately six were presented during a summer session. Student Concerts were informal performances of student-choreographed compositions performed by students.
      Arranged chronologically and within each year arranged into categories of Class Showings, Student Concerts, and Student Workshops.
    - Posters, 1949-1968, 7 folders (Box 33)
      Contains posters advertising the school curriculum and faculty.
    - Posters, 1959, 1961, 1963, 1967, 1968 (Box OS2)
    - Special and Master Classes, 1971-1974, 3 folders (Box 33)
      Contains sign-up sheets, schedules, and flyers advertising special and master classes that were offered in addition to the regular course offerings as a one-time opportunity for students to receive instruction from visiting dance artists, including Rudy Perez, Louis Falco, and Murray Louis.
    - Workshops for Professionals, 1953-1977, 0.58 Linear Feet (Box 33)
      Contains correspondence, course materials, printed materials, letters of interest, and student papers and evaluations pertaining to workshops held for dance and movement educators and dance accompanists. These were special "refresher" or "intensive" workshops tailored specifically for professionals in the dance field who were dance or movement teachers, dance accompanists, or dance therapists. Workshop instructors included Delia Hussey, Ruth Murray, Barbara Beiswanger, Theodora Wiesner, Bonnie Bird, Marion North, and Virginia Tanner.
    - Dean of the School (Martha Myers), 1968-1988 and undated, 27 folders (Box 34)
      Contains correspondence, recommendation letters, and notes relating to Myers' activities associated with the school and with her professional activities at Connecticut College and in the dance world.
  - Faculty, 1948-1977 (Box 34)
    - Appointments, 1948-1977, 18 folders (Box 34)
      Contains lists of teaching faculty, faculty assistants, and accompanists. Lists may contain information such as biographical blurbs or informal salary and expense information.
    - Faculty Files, 1948-1977 and undated, 4.25 Linear Feet (Box 34)
      Contains correspondence, contracts, housing forms, notes, memos to individual faculty members, and recommendations regarding teaching faculty, teaching assistants, accompanists, and workshop directors (Dance Educators, Dance Therapy, and Dance Accompanists). Also includes some biographical materials and some materials regarding ADF classes. Several faculty members played multiple roles at the festival (e.g. performer, workshop director, faculty member). Materials relating to the individual roles a participant played will be filed by the subject of the materials. For example, Helen Priest Rogers' correspondence about the Film and Notation project is filed in the Special Projects subgroup, and her correspondence relating to plans for teaching a Labanotation course will be filed in the Faculty Files. Her course materials, such as syllabi and handouts, is filed in Courses in the Curriculum subseries. Materials regarding faculty who were invited but could not attend and letters of interest from potential faculty members are filed in the School Administration series under Administration.
      Arranged chronologically and within each year alphabetically by surname of faculty member.
      From 1948 through the mid to late 1960s, ADF's faculty consisted of a core group of teachers, many of whom were also involved as regular festival performers and advisors to the festival and the school including Martha Graham, Jose and Pauline Limon, Doris Humphrey, Louis Horst, William Bales, Helen Priest Rogers, George and Barbara Beiswanger, Norman and Ruth Lloyd, Hazel Johnson, and George McGeary. ADF Directors Ruth Bloomer and Theodora Wiesner also taught during this period. Other faculty of note from this period are Alwin Nikolais, Murray Louis, Alvin Ailey, Donald McKayle, Glenn Mack, Jane Dudley, Sophie Maslow, Betty Jones, Ruth Currier, Doris Rudko, David and Marnie Wood, Martha and Josef Wittman, Lucas Hoving, Daniel Nagrin, Pauline Koner, Bessie Schonberg, and Yuriko. Later faculty included Walter Nicks, Meredith Monk, Arthur Hall, Anna Halprin, Peter Saul, and Mel Wong.
      - 1948-1958 (Box 34)
      - 1959-1965 (Box 35)
      - 1966-1973 (Box 36)
      - 1974-1977 and undated (Box 37)
    - Evaluations, circa 1956-1977, 17 folders (Box 37)
      Contains correspondence, notes, and evaluation forms from faculty members on the previous season and their recommendations for the next year's school and festival.
    - Memos to Faculty, circa 1948-1977, 36 folders (Box 37)
      Contains memos sent to faculty members and advisors as a group, not to individuals. Individual correspondence and memos sent to faculty members are filed in Faculty Files. Memos include announcements regarding class grades and credits, scheduling classes, tentative class schedules for faculty review, advising students, student registration, the season's teaching faculty and school, visitors and guests at the festival, complimentary tickets, housing and meals, and invitations to faculty meetings and social gatherings. In the 1970s, memos were often sent out as packets to faculty members before they arrived for the season.
    - Meetings, circa 1949-1975, 20 folders (Box 37)
      Contains agenda and meeting minutes of faculty meetings. Minutes exist as unedited drafts, handwritten and typed notes, and final copies that were distributed to the faculty or to the Director and Dean.
  - Students, 1939-1977 and undated (Box 38)
    - Class Lists, 1948-1977, 1.25 Linear Feet (Box 38)
      Contains lists of students who participated in classes at the ADF School, equivalent to attendance sheets or grade sheets. Grades are frequently on the class lists or grade books included.
      Arranged chronologically and within each year by the surname of faculty member.
    - Enrollment, 1939-1977, 0.42 Linear Feet (Box 39)
      Contains administrative enrollment lists and statistics regarding acceptance and enrollment in the ADF School and enrollment in individual classes and workshops (though not Special Project workshops). Also contains administrative information about class drop/adds.
    - Evaluations and Surveys, 1948-1976, 0.42 Linear Feet (Box 39)
      Contains completed student evaluation forms and administrative compilations of evaluations quoting students' reactions on their experiences as members of the ADF School. Also contains limited correspondence from students evaluating their experiences. Most evaluations are anonymous. May also include faculty evaluations where the author could not be distinguished as faculty or student.
    - General Information, 1948-1977 and undated, 0.25 Linear Feet (Box 39)
      Contains printed material, such as memos, schedules, forms, and information sheets, generated by the ADF School and disseminated to all students. Topics include registration, classes, housing, cafeteria, recreation, and other information relating to the student's life on campus.
    - G.I. Bill, 1948-1967, 6 folders (Box 39)
      Contains correspondence, letters of interest, official materials and information from the Veterans Administration, and applications of accepted G.I. Bill of Rights students who could not attend. Correspondence in this subseries is largely between Connecticut College officials and School of the Dance Directors regarding procedures for attending the School of the Dance on the GI Bill.
    - Handbooks and Packets, 1938-1977, 12 folders (Box 39)
      Contains handbooks or packets for ADF School students. Handbooks and packets contain general information compiled to orient students about the school, the festival, and the college where the school was held.
    - Other Activities, 1951-1971, 5 folders (Box 39)
      Contains memos, flyers, and correspondence concerning activities and excursions organized by ADF for the students outside the curriculum and the ADF School, including square dances, special films, and trips to Mystic Seaport and to other attractions in the surrounding region.
    - Scholarships and Financial Aid, 1948-1977, 2.5 Linear Feet (Box 40)
      Contains administrative documents and correspondence related to publicizing and arranging scholarships and financial aid for ADF School applicants, including forms and form letters, letters of interest from students about specific scholarships, all applications for the Doris Humphrey Fellow (except for the winner, whose materials are filed in her student record), and a sampling of student records of students who either applied for or were awarded financial aid (scholarships particularly) but were unable to attend. All correspondence relating to individual students who attended the School and received scholarships is filed in the Student Records subseries. Notable documents include letters of recommendation from Mary Wigman (1958), Martha Graham (1963), and Arthur Mitchell (1974).
      Arranged chronologically and then into the following subject categories: Apprenticeships and Assistantships, Cooperative Scholarships, Doris Humphrey Fellowships, Foreign Scholarships, Ruth Bloomer Loan Fund, and Scholarships.
      - 1948-1965 (Box 40)
      - 1966-1977 (Box 41)
    - Student Records, 1939-1977, 33.75 Linear Feet (Box 42)
      Contains student records for the Six-Week School, the Four-Week School for Young Dancers, participants in workshops such as Dance Educators and Dance Therapy, members of the Theatre Component, Doris Humphrey Fellows and all scholarship and financial aid students, faculty and staff members who took one or two classes, and part-time students. Not included are participants in Community Workshops, Special Projects, or Children's Classes.
      Arranged chronologically and then alphabetically.
      - 1939, 1940, 1948-1951 (Box 42)
      - 1952, 1953 (Box 43)
      - 1954, 1955 A-L (Box 44)
      - 1955 M-Z, 1956 (Box 45)
      - 1957, 1958 A-P (Box 46)
      - 1958 Q-Z, 1959 (Box 47)
      - 1960 (Box 48)
      - 1961 (Box 49)
      - 1962, 1963 A-B (Box 50)
      - 1963 C-Z, 1964 A-J (Box 51)
      - 1964 K-Z, 1965 A-L (Box 52)
      - 1965 M-Z, 1966 A-J (Box 53)
      - 1966 K-Z, 1967 A-R (Box 54)
      - 1967 S-Z, 1968, 1969 A-E (Box 55)
      - 1969 F-Z (Box 56)
      - 1970 A-R (Box 57)
      - 1970 S-Z, 1971 A-K (Box 58)
      - 1971 L-Z, 1972 A-B (Box 59)
      - 1972 C-R (Box 60)
      - 1972 S-Z, 1973 A-H (Box 61)
      - 1973 H-Z, 1974 A-G (Box 62)
      - 1974 H-Sc (Box 63)
      - 1974 Se-Z, 1975 A-K (Box 64)
      - 1975 L-V (Box 65)
      - 1975 W-Z, 1976 A-Nel (Box 66)
      - 1976 New-Z, 1977 A-Bra (Box 67)
      - 1977 Bre-Z (Box 68)
    - Young Choreographers, 1959-1967, 9 folders (Box 69)
      Contains audition sign-up sheets, audition rating sheets, memos, notes, correspondence, and programs pertaining to Young Choreographers' Concerts held during the summer session as a main stage performance. Participants in the Young Choreographers' auditions appear to be mostly students, but other participants were up-and-coming dancers who were not current students at the school. Auditioners and finalists include Trisha Brown (1962), Meredith Monk (1963), Martha Clarke (1962), Betty Jones (1960), Lar Lubovitch (1962), Carla Maxwell (1965), and Senta Driver (1965). The Young Choreographers' Concerts were active during the 1960s and are not related to the Young Choreographers and Composers program, 1983-1995.
- General Correspondence, circa 1948-1977, 28 folders (Box 69)
  Contains correspondence between audience and participants and ADF members. Materials include correspondence from audience members writing to express appreciation or unhappiness regarding ADF presentations and inquiries regarding programs, school visitation, and local accommodations. Series also includes congratulatory letters and telegrams from ADF personnel and students and personal letters to the directors regarding administrative details and personal appreciation for the festival. In addition, there are miscellaneous form letters to the community such as a 1951 form letter inviting local artists to sketch dance classes.
- Printed Material, 1930-1977 (Box 69)
  Contains most printed materials created by ADF. Some printed materials are in other series. For example, school catalogs are under School, Curriculum, Bulletins and Catalogs.
  - Advertisements, 1949-1977, 27 folders (Box 69)
    Contains ADF marketing materials for the school, festival performances, and special projects held during the summer festival, including brochures, newspaper inserts, handbills, and advertisements printed in newspapers and magazines. Also includes some Connecticut College materials, Connecticut and New England educational and tourism brochures, and national dance publications in which ADF placed advertisements.
  - ADF Publications, 1948-1967, 27 folders (Box 69)
    Contains ADF published items including booklets and newsletters.
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Dance Advance, 1948-1963 (13 folders) (Box 69)
    - A Decade of Dance: 1948-1957 (Box 69)
    - Footprints, 1967 (Box 69)
    - Nike on the Campus, circa 1967 (Box 69)
  - ADF Information, 1936-1977, 24 folders (Box 69)
    Contains materials that provide information about the school and festival in narrative, list, and statistical formats, including narrative materials about ADF's history, descriptions of special project programs that developed during the 1970s, lists of choreographic works and premieres performed at ADF, documentation of opening and closing dates for the ADF School, a listing of students who achieved recognition in the dance field, and fact sheets. The information from these documents was often used for publicity or grant-writing purposes.
  - Bibliographies and Catalogs, 1930-1974 and undated, 0.33 Linear Feet (Box 69)